hello and welcome it's May 28th 2024
we're in active live stream
57.1 welcome to the active inference
Institute we're a participatory online
Institute that is communicating learning
and practicing applied active inference
this is a recorded and archived live
stream please provide feedback so we can
improve our work all backgrounds and
perspectives are welcome and we'll
follow video etiquette for live
streams check out active inference dorg
to learn more about live streams and
other
projects okay today in 57.1 we're
continuing the discussion of the paper
on active data selection and information
seeking with K friston and Thomas par
joining so thank you both we did 57.0
covering some of the back round and to
begin the 57.1 whoever would like to go
first how about
Thomas lead us into the active data
selection setting SL Challenge and
introduce yourself however you would
like thank you the and go for
it okay so to introduce myself I'm I'm
Thomas I've been working active infs for
a few years um and I split my time
between research and clinical practice
which I think is part of the motivation
for some of the later parts of of this
paper uh relate to some of the clinical
type problems that might face with us um
I guess the background of this
particular paper is that a couple of
years ago now I I was in Australia to
present at the australasian Basin
Network modeling Society if I hope I've
got that right um who ran a really
fascinating conference using Basin
networks to model everything from
volcanoes to uh to Coastal erosion and
um and various other things um and there
are quite a few clinicians involved in
that conference as well in interested
things like um respiratory diseases and
Diagnostics um and one of the organizers
of that conference happened to be
running a special issue on basa networks
and kind of invited us to to take part
in it and so this was our contribution
to that and the idea is to take some of
the same principles that we use in
active inference and some of the
longstanding principles from from people
like Stu studs like Lindley um to apply
to the problem of experimental design
and to think about how active INF line
principles can be applied outside of
biology sorry I'm talking too fast for
you
time thank you um
okay Carl do you want to add anything to
that or
as we kind of begin no no no I I I
repeat I'm an admiring spectator
this okay okay Joy Thomas's Lucid
account of this very pertinent
application of some basic principles of
optimal basian design epistemic
foraging okay then no
hackling okay let's go to some of
Chris's questions and also as people ask
questions in the live chat we'll go in
there um okay
so let's just start with time sampling
how did you or in what equations or in
what conceptual ways did you bring in
time and the kind of time sampling that
was explored in this
paper so time is is a really interesting
um issue in terms of how you model a lot
of these sorts of processes um partly
because a lot of interesting processes
evolve in time but it also brings in
some really interesting issues in terms
of how you sample uh and how you how you
gather information
about uh and the most obvious problem
there is that some things change and
some things don't um so that brings you
into the world of of a lot of what
psychologists often deal with things
like inhibition of return the idea that
when you when you look at something you
learn something about it and uh the time
it takes for it to be worth looking back
there will depend upon how unexpectedly
things might change in that
location um so that's a really important
part of a lot of the sorts of generative
models that that we deal with both in
biology and out of out out of that area
because you need to be able to deal with
with worlds that
change um and that that s calls into
question how do you actually approach
time in generative models there are a
whole range of different approaches that
one can take that so I think a lot of a
lot of early work in active inference
was formulated in terms of continuous
time models working with differential
equations um generalized coordinates of
motion which is a where representing
trajectories in terms of positions
velocities accelerations as if you're
doing a TA
expansion and taking the coefficients of
that and that would be one one very good
way of representing a temporal
progression a lot of a lot of the more
recent work we do in actually been is
based upon discrete time models where
you see things as being a sequence of
events and you just represent what
happens at a sequence of different time
points um in this particular paper we
ended up using a slightly different
approach and that was to to um to
essentially use a basis set or a set of
basis functions to um to to allow there
to be some smooth progressions in
time um rather than dealing with
specific time steps themselves so it
sort of blurs the gap
between um between using um discrete
time steps where there's a clear
boundary on the side of it and
continuous progressions where where
there's no boundaries um by using a
series of basis functions placed at
different points in time you end up
getting this sort of smooth progression
from one uh sort of blurry time step to
the
next um
so I I I think time is sort of
incredibly important in how we how we
think about these sorts of things again
in terms of thinking about how things
change um but also in terms of thinking
what's the right way of representing
time in a generative
model awesome welcome Chris as
well this definitely is reminiscent of
figure 4.3 from the textbook which I'll
bring up how would you contrast it or
which figure should we look at to
explore which variables are continuous
or
discreet this figure is the one
you so this paper won't have anything
specific but you're right that that
probably is one from the textbook that
deals with with exactly that this
distinction um so here I think one of
the later figures does use a sort of um
basis set type representation to look at
tempal progressions
I can't remember which figure that is
I'm
afraid
okay did you did you want to talk
through this figure that's up maybe
summarize this
figure and so this figure was trying to
trying to demonstrate in a sort of
relatively simple um analytic case what
it might mean and and sort of taking
time out of it for the moment what it
might mean to select those data points
that are going to be most informative
about um some underlying model uh and
the way it's been set up here is to
start with um uh so the sort of upper
left plot here we're just showing a
function um with a whole series of
different possible parameters that might
exist so you can imagine these Theta
parameters that are sort of shown as one
being bigger than the next um each
represent which function might be used
here um and uh and you can see that in
some of the there's a lot of variation
in certain parts of the function so for
the green one you can see there's a sort
of very big peak around zero but
slightly smaller Peak for the purple one
slightly smaller for the
yellow um but actually there is also
certain points where where it's not so
obvious and you wouldn't really be able
to distinguish it so they all more or
less cross the x-axis at the same
point and and on both sides of zero so
if you were to choose CH somewhere on
this plot to work out which function you
were sampling from you're much better
off choosing from somewhere around zero
um then you are choosing at the point
where where it's actually crossing the
x-axis where the where all look very
very similar and so this is just to get
across the intuition behind this process
of of selecting your data efficiently to
be able to resolve between alternative
hypotheses the best you can or even to
estimate along some continuous parameter
value
as it would be here um so following the
the sort of sequence round this um this
graphic um the idea is that we can
represent these things into several
different kinds of generative model so
here we're representing either a basing
Network where you say my explanatory
variable is this Theta that's generating
some data
y um and then we' have this Pi variable
which like a lot of active infation
repres our policy or our choice of where
we want to sample so here this is
choosing somewhere along the x-axis that
we might want to um work out what the
corresponding why might to
be um the the factor graph
representation deals with exactly the
same
model but but now expressed by putting
the factors in explicitly and by factors
I mean that our probability distribution
which is made up of our PRI beliefs
about Theta and a likelihood which maps
from Theta to our data y um are now sort
of explicitly put in as squares that
represent the different bits of of that
generative
model the next step is to to use a
normal or a forny factor graph which
essentially just emits the circles so
now the variables are represented by the
edges the points that connect the
different factors so you can imagine if
we take our probability distributions so
probability of latent states of
parameters uh and the probability data
given those and we separate those out
into factors and we draw a square for
each of the factors of that probability
distribution and connect those up
whenever they share a variable so the
edges or the connections between the
factors are the random variables might
want to
estimate and then I'm trying to see
behind the um
cameras across so the um the next step
is is to use the forny factor graph
because it's it's often quite a nice
notation to use when trying to
understand um message passing and the
different things that contribute to um
to the way we estimate these these
variables so here for each different
Square we can see there being messages
being passed between the neighboring
edges and when we combine those edges we
can we can arrive at a posterior
estimate of the marginal of the variable
we're dealing with so this would be how
we might go about estimating the theeta
there but the key twist here is that
we're now not just interested in message
passing for the process of inference but
we can also now start to interpret those
messages um in terms of how they
contribute to various different entries
that together make our information G so
here we have um both a conditional
entropy sometimes refer to as an
ambiguity and that conditional entropy
essentially says um if I were to sample
over here in a more biological setting
if I were to look over here um how
confident am I in in terms of what I
would see or what how confident am I
that these parameters will map to
something meaningful and
informative um the predictive entropy is
is another form of of entropy or
uncertainty that essentially says before
I've looked at anywhere regardless of
the parameters even if I've marginalized
them out how uncertain am I about the
data I'm going to get so the conditional
entropy is how precise is the mapping or
how imprecise is the mapping between
parameters and data predictive entropy
is just my uncertainty a prior a
priority about what I'd see if I if I
looked over
that those things are quite
interpretable when you start thinking in
terms of experimental designs because a
um predictive entropy I I if I'm already
very certain about what I'd see or what
what would happen if I performed a
particular experiment there's almost no
no point in doing that experiment
there's only a point uh acting to find
something out if I don't already know
what I'm going to
observe so this predictive entropy um is
a positive thing that if if I'm
uncertain about what I'd see then I
should go out and seek that out I should
get those data points because there's
something potentially to
learn however there are are certain
circumstances where where all you get is
noise and you may be completely
uncertain about what you're going to get
you know you if
you just keep running a random number
generator over and over again you're
never going to become much more certain
about what you're going to see
next uh and so that's not a terribly
useful thing to seek out and that's
where this conditional entropy or
ambiguity comes in in that it penalizes
those things that are not going to
resolve any uncertainty it's the way
often thing about it is if you take the
predictive entropy you have the total
amount of uncertainty about what I'm
going to observe if you then subtract
the conditional entropy from that then
you you you're left with the amount of
uncertainty that you might be able to
resolve and I think this comes back in
in a bit more detail and we can discuss
that a little bit more in some of the
later figures if we get to those um but
essentially the difference between these
two things is our expected Information
Gain uh which is also a mutual
information
can often be expressed as the difference
between those two entropies how much am
I going to update my beliefs how much am
I going to change what I I believe as a
consequence of making a particular
observation thank you Thomas that was a
great summary I think we'll return to
this I wanted to bring up figure 4.3
from the
textbook ah yes yeah so this is and yes
anything on this and to kind of
juxtapose
the conditional entropy with the a
matrix and the sense making and the
mapping and then the predictive entropy
to the B
Matrix and the transition among latent
States yes that's right so um for those
who haven't haven't seen these before
these are again of factor graph type
representations where we're now dealing
with um temporal
progressions um and so the the graph at
the top represents a series of States as
they transition from one to the next
over time there may be more or less
uncertainty in those transitions so I
might be very confident as to how a
sequence progresses if there's very low
volatility Dynamics are very
precise um and then and so those the the
factors label
three and the factors label two
represent the way in which my data
regenerated given some states of the
world so I might not be able ble to
directly observe the s's but they will
give rise to the O's or the observable
outcomes um
and exactly as D says there's a a link
between the um the two different terms
in um in this expected information game
so the conditional entry will depend
almost entirely upon this mapping from
states to outcomes upon this um
conditional entropy um will depend upon
this light C
distribution and so it will say that if
I'm in this state then there's a very
precise mapping to the data whereas in
in alternative states there might not be
and so that allows me to then select
between between these things based upon
policy Pi I
choose um the the sorry the predictive
entry will actually be a function of
both forms of uncertainty so uncertainty
in the transitions so if things change
since I last looked there and my
predictive entropy might be very high
and I might want to look back there
sooner again in psychological terms
that's a sorry the lights have gone off
I'll see if I can turn those back on um
the um so the
the um predictive enty deals with that
sort of inhibition of return um if it's
due to the transition uncertainty
however if it's due to the uncertainty
in the um in the likelihood then that
will remain relatively fixed over time
and I won't be able to resolve that
sorry let me see if I can sort out
those it's
better so the figure on the the sort of
lower part of the screen so the the
below graph is actually a similar
representation but now in continuous
time
so here we're now dealing with the the
states X might be continuous variables
the X Prime is the um rate of change of
my um my state X the X double Prime is
the acceleration and if you know all of
these things and further coordinates of
motion you can start to construct a
trajectory or or or predict anticipate
both the future or the near future based
upon these variables and the recent past
as
well um and exactly as D's written there
it's it's effective Taylor series
expansion where these are the
coefficients of that AA
Series so these would be sort of the two
ends of the spectrum dealing with sort
of a purely discrete time process and a
continuous time process there are
various ways of either blurring those
boundaries or
even um even of combining the two
so maybe now H having brought this out
could you return to the basis
sets and comment on how it's similar or
different to the time handling in the
discrete time or the continuous time
setting yeah so um so the use of Base
assets will often imply that you're
dealing with A continuous function but
rather than have variables that
represent either positions and
velocities and those things I mean what
one could argue that actually a
generalized coord the motion system is a
form of basis set in itself it's just a
polinomial basis set So you you're just
waiting sums of of different um orders
in a polinomial
series um but there are other basis sets
that that one could use and those
include things like um fora basis sets
or cosine basis sets where it would be
difficult to sort of localize things in
a specific point in time but is much
more frequency based um or as as happens
to be done in particular paper um it's a
series of gausian basis
functions and those are centered on
different points in time but because
they're Goin
shaped the the boundaries between them a
little bit blurred so the value at any
particular Point how much you weight
that particular function localized
around a specific time point will also
have an effect on the neighboring time
points and that's effectively a way of
putting in a belief that that there
although there's a temporal progression
and perhaps a series of discrete steps
there's actually a smoothness to that as
well there are no discrete jumps in this
that actually are just adding
subtracting functions that vary
smoothly to construct that overall
picture and that gives you quite a
flexible way of representing a lot of a
lot of often quite nonlinear
functions I think from memory that um
har actually used sort of basic set type
function
um in some of the covid modeling as well
in some of the later papers to model
things like seasonal
fluctuations changes in um
transmissibility over time so they have
quite a there's quite a broad um way of
using them the the downside of using a
lot of those functions that they're
often less mechanistically interpretable
so there something that that are often
quite convenient in terms of getting a a
flexible function
representation wouldn't necessarily
speak to a specific
mechanism thank you Thomas yeah also
basis sets are brought up in
SPM and I think one advantage that's
raised there is how it allows the
prespecification of all of the
oscillatory patterns of a given
frequency range and then filtering the
data with that pre-specified seeve in a
way
um interesting and and compressing
information about the hypothesis of what
structure the data could have like
nearby things being more related events
in time being more related if they're
close so on yes and compression is a
good point there that actually as soon
as you start using a basis set you've
now got the option to to stop after a
certain number of
functions um so in generalized
coordinates of motion
that there's a limit to how many um
additional coordinates is normally
useful to put in because the the degree
of accumulation of the uncertainty means
that once you be on a certain point it
becomes so uncertain that it doesn't
necessarily contribute to the earlier
terms
sequence um and that sort of arises as a
function of of Auto correlations over
time um and and you're right to say that
using um using things like frequency
based forer type basis sets also gives
you that opportunity for compression um
and I think a lot of a lot of imag image
processing does use things like the
discrete cosine um transform which is
based upon series of cosine basis sets
um where you can throw away certain um
orders of of that or certain frequency
bands um without losing too much
information
awesome okay let's go to a second
question by Chris but Carl or or Chris
just raise your hand or
totally go for
it um let's go to the second one
or let's ask this question by upcycle
Club do you think that there might be
any algorithmic modifications metah
aristic or hybrid approaches that could
potentially lead to even better data
selection optimization
[Music]
probably um I I suppose it's a matter of
thinking about
what so hybrid approaches um it's a it's
a question of what what it's being
hybrid with um and I I imagine we may
come on to to some of those questions um
later on as well
um so metah heuristics well I suppose a
heuristic um from a basin perspective is
is just a prior and so I think it's
exactly right to say that with the right
priors in place for the right sorts of
models and the right sorts of settings
um this process can be made much more
efficient um so if you if you know a
reasonable amount about the structure of
your problem um then you don't
necessarily need to rely on on um basis
sets and that sort of thing that
actually often you can write down
something with a good deal of
information in it already and then your
model doesn't necessarily need to learn
all of that it just it's able to then
use the resulting predictive entropies
and conditional entropies to to pin down
more specific things that that you
wanted to know find
out
um so yes I'm sure that there it it's
probably not going to be a one siiz fits
all in many ways that the prior are
going to be those that are most
appropriate to the particular problem
you're dealing with particular agent you
have but ultimately they all I think
lead
come under the same underlying problem
and the same underlying principle which
is that um that if you select things in
order to optimize your model of the
world then it's about finding the best
fit with your model of the world uh and
that fit would would normally be
Quantified using something like a free
energy or a marginal that beard so I
think it all comes from the same
principle but if you're a different sort
of creature or a different sort of agent
than the implicit model you and the way
in which that directs your exploration
to find out more to to improve your
model fit uh can be very
different Chris or Carl want
to ask anything or bring up
anything uh not quite yet I'm kind of
thinking through um you know talking
about the time series and that sort of
thing so I think we can kind of keep
going on
Yeah
Carl
[Music]
um sorry I was just thinking about
heuristics and um what it means to
people in uh a certain kind of Economics
something think about gigar renza and
the like which I just read as as as
prior the right kind of Prior um that
have a minimal complexity um but I was
just talking had what is a metah
heuristic it's a heuristic next door to
a heuristic So Daniel or Thomas can
somebody Define for me Hyper prior
perhaps yes that's what it must be it
must be a hyper PRI that's what I'd
assume okay thank you although you know
what even is a hyper prior it's
effectively just a prior isn't it yeah I
suppose it's a prior in the context of a
you a certain kind of hierarchal
generative model absolutely yeah
also there's a very practical element I
think about chapter 6 of the textbook
and the recipe for modeling so maybe to
kind of bring in this practical
element in the modeling of these
adaptive data
sampling what is the recipe for active
inference generative modeling maybe even
as you've learned or updated in the 2
years since chapter
6 I I mean I think the basic recipe is
still the same um so
uh so the often I think what we do is is
think about what sort of um what sort of
model that we're interested in and what
sort of question that's supposed to
address um and ultimately when you're
using modeling in the context of of
the data sorts of questions you might
want to ask are things like um which of
several alternative models is the best
explanation um so doing a sort of
discrete hypothesis test uh or um trying
to actually recover particular parameter
estimates so so coming up with posterior
distributions over in an active
inference context that will be over
particular kinds of beliefs um that then
determine Behavior
um and that's particularly important in
the context of things like um um
computational phenotyping in clinical
populations so trying to understand
which beliefs um might might be and by
beliefs I mean here sort of implicit
Basin beliefs not necessarily something
um explicit that you might be able to
articulate um but what sort of beliefs
might vary between different populations
that then lead to particular kinds of um
what we might think of as pathological
behavior um and so you can start then
ask questions in terms of if you can
phenotype different people you can start
to use those beliefs almost as if they
were data that you can then ask other
questions so how how does this vary with
a particular diagnosis therapeutic
intervention um
so there was a figure in the book which
I can't remember the sequence of Now
setting out sort of sequence that you
might follow if you were you were trying
to develop a model and um and then use
that to actually answer a question based
upon some empirical data but I think the
the key idea is um you're going to bring
that up um I think that the key idea was
if you have your model can predict some
behavior from it you can then use use
that model of um that that is
effectively someone's brains model of
the world but then you're modeling
someone else modeling world and here we
are yeah uh so I think in the
um yeah this this
one 9.1 so so so so the figure you've
sort of copied into the lower left there
is um is quite a nice way of thinking
about um this process and active
inference of modeling other PE other
people or things doing modeling um so
someone's brain um that you're trying to
explain is itself self modeling the
world so from that brain's perspective
the data that need to be explained are
sensory data so visual data SM sensory
data auditory data whatever um and then
as a scientist you're trying to explain
the way in which that brain is behaving
and generating behavioral outputs or
electrophysiological signals or or
whatever you might be measuring as a
neuroscientist um and so my model of the
brain's model ends up becoming the key
thing and that's sort of sketched out in
this particular
figure um and the other figure that you
had up um for a moment sort of talking
through the sequence that one might
adopt um in terms of how you might
construct this uh and it's not
necessarily linear I think as the arrows
show um but essentially you need to need
to think about what sort of task you
want to uh form what experiments you
want to perform
um you need to think about what model
that's
optimizing um and here it's showing the
partially observed Mark of decision
process model which might in this case
be the internal model of as rattin a
maze from that you then need to
construct a likelihood function which
says given that the rat had this sort of
model and these parameters in it uh
what's the likelihood that it would um
behave in a particular way so that that
um P of you is the probability that they
would have behaved in a particular way
given that
model and then we might equip that
likelihood of some prior beliefs about
parameters in that rats model um and
combining the prior and the lik we can
then invert that model in much the same
way we do any other sort of Bas in
inflence um and and there are further
analyses we could then do on that so so
this is what I was sort of sketching out
um earlier on that if you have ramet
estimates and you know the posterior for
a number of different RS in a maze or or
patient populations or um or even
artificial systems of some sort you can
then perform other analyses on that
almost as if those posteriors were data
points themselves and you can start to
ask how do these beliefs vary as a
function of diagnosis or experimental
condition or whatever else
thank
you
okay
let's in the in these beginning Parts
focus on what the model is and then as
we kind of move towards the end in the
second time talking we'll look more at
the clinical trial and maybe the
questions with um that are more open for
the future how about connection with
machine learning so Chris
wrote um your
examples primarily focus on statistical
modeling how do you see active data
selection methods integrating with other
machine learning models especially deep
learning architectures that typically
require large data sets are there
specific challenges or considerations in
this
context I mean I I would argue that
almost in a in a sense the the answers
in in the question that that these large
data sets that they they often seem to
acquire um is exactly the opposite sort
of Principle as to to um what we'd be
working with in this sort of Pap so the
idea is how do I work with more
efficient data sets how do I design not
just models but also the selection of
data to make sure that even with a
smaller data stat it can be more
informative um so there's I think
there's a bit of a difference in the
underline philosophy but I would also
say that that most machine learning
models are forms of statistical modeling
in some sense whether or not they
explicitly represent the uncertainty
that um that you get out of them um I
mean I I think it it is also what you
know the comment about um hybrid
approaches that was was discussed on one
of the previous questions as well one
way of of thinking about that might be
in terms of using things like neural net
work architectures and function
approximators as part of the uh as part
of a a basinal statistical model um and
and that's sometimes referred to as a
process of amotization
you can fix certain parts of your
function approximation and in a sense
using the basis sets is also a form of
function
approximation that then simplifies um
simplifies or in some ways makes it
cheaper to do the process next time you
need to do that inference you can sort
of save a function that says given this
input this is the outcome I should I
should end up with or this is the
inference I should arrive
at
um one of the challenges there is being
able to go in the other direction and to
be able to say if I'm going to actively
select data then I need to be in a
position where I can predict or generate
the outcomes I might to
get um and that might be something that
that is um possible to do in the context
of of generative approaches in in in
machine learning um and I suppose all of
the approaches we've been discussing
really are generative
approaches but but because I can now
generate not just the outcome itself but
I can generate a distribution over the
outcome conditioned upon what I might
do that's one of the key things in in
being able to um being able to select
those data appropriately and if you're
using a model where it's very difficult
to project that into that space and to
ask um what are these conditional
entropies then it does become very
difficult to select data appropriately
so using something that's sort of very
highly nonlinear and and difficult to be
able to to work with those things it
does become more challenging to do that
sometimes people might sort of res might
sort of approach it using um um sort of
sampling based methods to come up with
an empirical distribution but by the
time you start doing that you end up
with something that is much more
costly so if you're if the problem
you're working with is one where you
want to try and bring it down to uh to
use fewer data points and to select your
data more intelligently uh then often
that does require particular kinds of
model that let you do that in in a very
efficient
way there it's an interesting area and
it be be interesting to see how how how
you might interact these sorts of
approaches um one thing you might
imagine is that that actually if you've
got a very clear unambiguous mapping
that you can learn with a deep learning
type model it might be that you could
actually just treat the outcome or the
labels that that are produced by that
deep learning model as data from the
perspective of another model might go
about selecting the right sorts of of
labels that are going to be helpful in
terms of learning about
things so there may be levels of a model
that that can be when they're
sufficiently
ambiguous sufficiently precise
mapping where you might not need to go
detail and and um and select things in
that way but it may be that the outputs
of that are things then need to be
combined um to form interesting
mechanistic hypotheses about what
happens
next that's very interesting like
thinking about different kinds of
Communications and reliabilities of
different kinds of analyses or computer
systems and then it's it's actually the
active data
sampling conditional entropy in practice
which is that reliable sources are
pursued as part of the information
foraging
adaptive playout that every agent has to
be involved in like reliability is its
own
suitability for an information
resource and then the other side of it
is actually resolving the the
variability of the latent States however
those may have extremely high
fundamental
variability so often pursuing the the
conditional
entropy the agent has more control
over because they can resolve
something more at least they can resolve
that yes it's knowing what what is and
isn't resolvable I think that that's key
because if you were to just seek out
things that were very uncertain you
might be sat there pressing the random
number generator over and over again
without being able to learn anything new
from it
and attractor state that you end up
being stuck in
unless you can contextualize that with
how resolvable it
is I think one of the simulations we we
put together in this particular paper um
explicitly varied the um uncertainty as
a function of where you are along
particular number
line and and that was just to illustrate
the point that actually there is
a so before this section I think yes it
would have been this one right um so
here you can see that we we're dealing
with a function where the variance grows
as you move away
from from about X is
zero and if you know that then you know
that that actually the the
informativeness of the data at the
peripheries is much less because you're
not going to be able to resolve a lot of
that uncertainty no matter how much you
look
there uh and so if you see in the the
choices plot in the lower right here um
the solution it arrives at looks like a
very sensible deliberate solution which
is to start in the Middle where things
are most precise then fan outwards
moving left and right to resolve as much
and certain as it can uh before it's
then resolved enough the cost of
sampling further data is is more the
amount of uncertainty that might be
resolvable where is it the ambiguity of
the conditional enty were consistent
across the entire line then you might
expect a much more even pattern sampling
and something that that in practice
might not very different from random
samping except for the sort of
sequential
effects i' I'd love to hear a first pass
on how this figure addresses some of the
similarities and differences between
active data sampling and maximum entropy
sampling
yes so um I don't know whether you have
one of the graphics of one of the
previous figures where it doesn't have
this imity to have
um but
so perfect yeah um so so this figure
shows an example where the ambiguity is
actually the same everywhere so the way
in which the data are generated and you
can see that because the you can see
that that in the sample data plot there
is a sort of well- defined function but
the amount of variance around that
function is more or less constant
throughout that entire line throughout
that
function um so in this circumstance the
conditional enty or ambiguity is the
same everywhere that means that the only
thing that really differs when you're
deciding where to look next and where to
sample next is actually the predictive
entropy um and so here it will just
choose locations about which it's most
uncertain and that's quite a sensible
thing to do because there's Noh that's
limited any more than anywhere else in
terms of the amount of resolvable
uncertainty um and so you can see that
the the prediction it arrives at after
making a series of choices and and you
can also see the series of choices it
makes a fairly well distributed um uh
that they're quite quite evenly spaced
and cover a lot of that
ground um
and so the the prediction it comes to
actually matches that uncertainty quite
well um in a maximum ENT so this is this
is completely identical in this
particular setting the maximum entropy
approach of selecting those locations
that have the maximum predictive entropy
that's very different to what we were
seeing on the previous figure that the
Daniel was showing the one where where
it starts in the center and fats
outwards um because if you were to adopt
a maximum elentary approach here then
then you can see that you'd spend much
more time sampling in the far
peripheries which is actually not a
terribly useful thing to do here because
um because you're going to
just get a lot of Uncertain data you're
not going to be able to resolve it very
effectively and so here the big
difference is that ambiguity AV verion
forces you to start in the least
ambiguous places and only once you've
got the most information you can out
that you start Fanning outwards and
going for the the more um uncertain
regions either side where there's
actually less information overall that
you can gain um because most of the
uncertainty is now
unresolved the other thing that we we
we've done with with this plot and I
think the other one as well is um
specify cost to sampling cost to
choosing the next data point um and and
this is very much like we do in active
inference simulations where we might um
trade off uh exploration and
exploitation so trade off having
preferences for one thing over over
another um and this is just to get
across that idea that that there often
are going to be
energetic or computational or even
Financial costs um to going out and
getting more
data
um and those costs are specified just as
prior beliefs about what I will tend to
do in the absence of any potential
information that I might gain so being a
prior belief that can just be added to
the log uh probability of me stopping
sampling can just be added to the um the
the the mutual information or expected
Information Gain which then gives you an
automatic tradeoff between um
exploitation and exploration and
effectly means that if I keep exploring
one here we are exactly so this C here
so once the expected information g once
the amount of uncertainty I can resolve
drops
below um the probability that I I would
um stop sampling then I will effectively
just stop sampling so you get an
automatic cut off as to when you want to
stop um doing your
experiments that's a very interesting
piece this was this was kind of a cool
aspect of it and thank you for that
connection to the maximum entropy Chris
want to ask anything or we can ask a
question from the live chat or one of
your prior
questions um not sure it's necessarily a
question but more I appreciate your
answer for that um that last question
that we were just discussing because it
it makes a lot of sense and it almost
seems like at some point in more complex
models that you can't really necessarily
know exactly what you're feeding um some
sort of like machine learning or
neuronet you might want to take a hybrid
approach where you have something that
you select a small amount select down
your sample U your data down to a
certain size and then you can kind of
tweak it can optimize your model a
little bit more by throwing a couple of
random things in there but at least you
have a smaller set that you're starting
from um kind of get I mean is that
something that you can kind of see doing
is like instead of trying to sample down
to something that's most informative
sample out what is the least
informative yes and I suppose that
that's the same sort of approach isn't
it as as to this starting in the the
least ambiguous place with the low
hanging fruit
and then moving out from there until you
feel you're not really gaining anything
further and I and I think you're
absolutely right because is as long as
you're able to specify the cost of
carrying on sampling and seeking out new
data that gives you quite a principled
way of working out when you stop doing
that um because a pure Maxim momentary
approach will carry on going um because
there's lots more entry there's lots
more
uncertainty and so you might want to
resolve that unless there is um cost to
doing so any perfectly reasonable thing
to do it there is no cost to doing so
you can just keep looking um but as soon
as you're dealing in a realistic setting
where actually by doing this you're not
doing something else or you're investing
some resource be that energetic
computational Financial um then then
taking account of that can be quite a
useful way of of doing that um I mean
it's an interesting point about in more
complex and large models and I suppose
one of the key points there is that the
best models are always going to be the
simple models you can get away with um
so if you have very large models with
lots of parameters the advantage is
they're very expressive can fit lots and
lots of
um functions or or different patterns of
data um the downside is first of all
that they become less interpretable but
second of all that you expose yourself
to problems of over
fitting and one one of the key things in
the active inference approach is that by
minimizing free energy uh marginal
likelihoods you're implicitly minimizing
complexity so the best models always be
the simplest you can get away with and
by get away with I mean as simple as you
can get without compromising the
accuracy right and that Mak lot sense
but but that's the key point isn't it so
sometimes actually there is quite a
complex process generating data and you
do need a relatively complex model to be
able to capture that without
compromising the
accuracy um so in in that setting it you
know a really good question as to how
would you go about actually selecting
data um in a model that that is
sufficiently expressive that it's fit
for purpose in a particular domain um
and I think a large part of that is
being able to to actually quantify the
um the likelihoods and the uncertainties
in terms of how that model works and
that is a challenge in in a lot of deep
learning based models of neural network
papers models but not all of them some
of them will explicitly account for
these sorts of things as well
Coral yeah anything go for
it yeah no that was just um very nicely
expressed you a key issue here I was um
I was just T taking my mind back to um
when I first learned about Active
Learning um as you of the kind described
by people like David
McKay um where you know the objective
was to try and find the right data
features that will resolve the
uncertainty in exactly the way that
we've been talking about because we've
been talking about it largely in the
context of inference um your inferring
latent states of Affairs out there given
some data um and clearly the original
notion of active learning um pertains to
learning the parameters of a generative
model we can also apply the same notion
to model selection or structure learning
um and that resonates very much with you
know the conversation um with Chris
Chris tier
um you know one can either look at
um seeking out those informative data
the data features that are good and good
simply in the sense that they inform um
your generative model in terms of
ultimately maximizing the evidence or
the marginal likelihood of your
generative model or you can look at it
as triaging bad data that's
uninformative um and you can imagine
that process a little bit like Maxwell's
demon so the data that you don't go and
actively seek out or if you're in a big
data setting and you're trying to ingest
or simulate large data what this notion
of um Active Learning and active
selection brings to the table is that
you don't just blindly ingest all the
data as current
um deep learning does you carefully
assess should I ingest this data point
or not um and you know implicit in what
to was Thomas was saying possibly
explicit but I'll have to ask him um
well have think what what what's that
kind of objective function what is the
if you like um another way of talking
about The Information Gain that I would
get if I accepted as Maxwell's demon
this next bit of data and that uh
Information Gain is just a mutual
information so what you're saying is
that you want to only take those data
that are literally good because they are
informative that will technically or
operationally increase the mutual
information of inherent in your model
between cause and consequence so I think
that you there's something really quite
fundamental about this sort of whole
notion of being active in the way that
you deal with data and gather
information that you know that
underwrites active inference as you know
um with its special focus on active
sensing and Active Vision and active
inference and active learning that you
can actually go right through to active
natural selection you know and one has
to wonder now whether there's a
homologue in in evolutionary thinking of
this kind of active
learning thanks for those points th
those are those are great yeah Thomas go
for
it I don't think I had anything really
to answer that I it's exactly the
because it's it's being able to decide
also upon your model space isn't it
think it's it's part of the point that
Carl's making there that actually it's
the selecting your model but is also
knowing which models even to select
between is another is another key part
of
it that's certainly been
a interesting area in terms of structure
learning
sted absolutely and I I really like the
a call to evolutionary biology I think
that there may be an analog there you
can kind of wrap your mind around some
of the things that you're doing if you
frame it kind of from an evolutionary
standpoint too it's alternative way of
looking at it but I think it's quite
valid
yeah also um speak that those two points
there they speak to um a key issue in
structure learning read as Bas in model
selection do you do you take a top down
approach or do you take a bottom up do
you grow your models carefully by
accepting this mutation or this extra
state in a factor or indeed an extra
level in a deep generative model in the
face of this data this evidence of how
good this uh model is you know almost in
the sense of adaptive Fitness in an
evolutionary context or do you use good
old Basin model reduction um and start
with something that can do everything
and then prune away in the bits that you
don't want um I just thinking it from a
biometic point of view or an
evolutionary slash developmental at
least neurod developmental perspective
sort of Evo Devo it looks as though um
biology does both doesn't it so we start
off with a brain which is over param I
over wired overc connected um and then
carefully prune away using basic model
reduction what we don't want um and yet
of course at the level of um exploring
that model or hypothesis space I would
imagine we rely a lot on carefully
crafted um mutations split and merge
like operators that you know gently feel
out into into different you know and
from that perspective each of us is a
data point point for evolution that's
quite chilling isn't
it lot to say on this um one really
practical note with the cost of sampling
and the opportunity to stop is to have
different information foraging locations
that have different costs like different
apis you could call or different costs
associated with taking on or holding a
record so it's really true a multiple of
you alluded to like it does reframe the
question into creating this semantic
kernel of understanding for example the
clinical trial setting something that
can be shown up on a graphical
representation and then being able to
use that purely in the generative
forward direction to generate synthetic
data with whatever other evaluative
criteria apply to that or just to learn
active inference and then also to use
that generativity not just to make more
data which is often of limited utility
for retraining but actually it includes
that adjacency of being able
to ask how much another piece of
information or evaluating the last
incoming piece of information or rank
the informativeness however in a way it
moves all the challenge into how you
define the gener model surprise surprise
because you could have a model of
information in the world that would lead
to very various uh attractor States
repetitive looking fixed looking and so
on so it's it's pretty interesting how I
guess that's the high road and the low
road kind of coming to meet each other
in the information foraging
setting because the fundamental
constraints and tradeoffs associated
with sampling they do come into play and
it does not solve the question it just
sets up some of
the objective functions that can be used
and have
interpretability for the these
uncertainty
[Music]
situations okay I'll ask another
question from the live
chat all right Demetrios
asks what is the nature of the Precision
waiting mechanism in this process is it
possible that high Precision of the
prior blocks the prediction error to
convey the newsworthy
[Music]
information so um precision and the
balance between prior likelihoods and
what determines which precis we might
use and I know I suppose relating that
explicitly back to this this question of
information seeking so um so Precision
can be applied to any probability
distribution essentially so so you could
have a precise prior you could have a
precise likelihood or impr precise
versions of either of those and this
gets particularly interesting and and
sometimes quite confusing in the context
of hierarchical models where the prior
from one level is effectively the
likelihood or conditional distribution
From perspective the level
above um and so so you end up questions
am I increasing prior or am I decreasing
with the effect of the lik or and it it
often depends upon exactly where you are
in these s models but taken to its
simplest level you imagine you have a
prior and likelihood some the data that
you're evaluating likelihood in relation
to
um the relative precision and it is the
relative Precision that's important
between the prior and likelihood will
determine which one of those has more
than final beliefs on your posterior we
have a very precise prior it says I'm so
confident about this that the matter
what I
see uh I'm not going to shift my beliefs
and relating this back to the concept of
of information seeking that would be the
situation where um
where it we a dynamic s
um I think there's been so little change
from the last time I saw something that
even if I saw something new it would
make any
difference um the likelihood if that is
very very
precise um leads to very low ambiguity
so if I believe there are very precise
uh regions of space from from the
perspective of my likelihood or regions
of whatever um whatever sort of process
I'm selecting between the different
policies I could I could
adopt um then I'm more likely to select
those locations compared to
others
um and this is often in in context of
neurobiology and psychology these are
often how people talk about processes
like attention so being able to say that
my likelihood is very precise in context
of spatial attention associated with
these particular spatial channels or
this area of space then that means I'm
going to update my beliefs much more
based upon this thing that I'm paying
attention
to
um the link back to information seeking
is that that because I might update my
beliefs much more based upon this
location in space I might act in such a
way that I get more information from it
I might move my eyes to look over there
um or or take whichever action is
relevant to whichever data set is I'm
dealing with um and we can think of that
as is essentially saying this region of
space this region of of policy space is
is more Salient than others because when
I choose to do something that leads to
that outcome I'm going to update my
beliefs much more as a
consequence um so I think that that sort
of gives you a brief summary of of how
priers and likelihoods interact with one
another the the notion of prediction era
came up as well which I think is is you
know an important one to think about
particularly when you're dealing with um
with continuous States based models and
perhaps most simply when it's a a simple
linear gausian model because the degree
of update um that you might make is
effectively going to be
um a linear error function where that
error is the difference between what I
predicted and what what actually
happened and that waiting is going to be
weighted by the Precision of the
likelihood so the degree of update I'm
going to make to my beliefs depends both
on the Precision
um how unambiguous I think it is and on
the degree of dis on the amount of
discrepancy from what I'd originally
predicted and that's the same idea that
then underwrites a lot of um a lot of
predictive coding and a lot of
neurobiological
models um of course even that needs to
be weighted very carefully by the prior
precision and um the equivalent errors
that you get once you deviate from your
prize uh and that probably brings us
back to this notion of lexity and the
need to keep things simple because one
reading of of keeping your model simple
is that you keep things as close as
possible to your
PRI if you have lots of parameters and
they're all deviating from that PRI
quite a lot in order to come up with an
explanation then that's effectively a
very complex model one that I think
would be penalized relative to a simpler
model where everything stays much closer
to the prize you have
thanks Let's uh Go a different direction
there was a very interesting and
ambiguous use of the streetlight
effect so what is the streetlight effect
and how how is
it kind of a representative
setting and what do we do I love the
graphics oh there were so many fun fun
representations so what what what is it
is it is it a um joke how how did you
find what how did you find one with a
pie oh just typing in a different
symbols to see underneath the
spotlight very good yeah gbt
40 um so the the idea of the street
light actually comes back to this idea
of ambiguity
aversion and it's an idea that um can't
remember where it first came from but I
first came across trust and psychology
literature um I think possibly a
reviewer mentioned it in a paper at some
stage um but the the street light effect
is originally set up to be something to
describe an unhelpful bias um and the
idea was that if you're sort of coming
home late at night uh and it's a dark
Street and you drop your keys the first
place you might look is underneath the
street
light and that unhelpful in the original
reading because your keys are not more
likely to go on the street light than
they are anywhere else and so it's a
metaphor for seeking out those sources
of information that are most easy to to
um to acquire and and um that you can
learn the most from very quickly of
course from an active inance perspective
that's actually a completely optimal
thing to do that if you have some
uncertainty to resolve very first thing
you should do is look under the street
light because then you you'll establish
that your car keys or or your house keys
are not there uh and then you might
start looking
elsewhere um so another way of putting
that is that the least ambiguous place
the place where there's the clearest
mapping between the location of my keys
and the visual data I would get is under
that street light so if I'm ambiguity
averse if I choose those places where
that conditional entropy is lowest then
I'll start the space under the street
light and maybe I'll then f out from
there just as we saw in the
simulation results that you put up
earlier
on yes what a what a comical plot twist
that it's like it's a joke because it
brings us to the point of laughing at
the person looking under the street
light and then it leaves it open like
but what should they have
done and then this isn't exactly what
they should have done um in this paper
but just like you said it's a reasonable
starting location especially if it's
where one finds one to
be so it's kind of interesting
um Carl or
Chris no I I I love that yeah yeah and I
haven't heard it phrase like that before
it's very nice
Chris no nothing really I I I do like
that analogy
though
let's how was equation three and this
seemingly very general
usage of of Information Gain
on uh Bas graphs how did that come into
play and maybe if you could just Define
how that was
used so the idea here was
that that just as in um a lot of Bas and
inflence problems where you're do
relatively complex gure models
um appropriately complicated generry
models that help accurately explain data
um that there's often quite a lot of
sparsity in those models and there might
be multiple different different nodes
and edges um that one might need to take
advantage of or sorry that represent
variables one might want to draw
inferences
about and so there's a long
um sort of series
of papers and advances have been looking
at ways to do that efficiently from an
inference
perspective uh and that that has led to
many many forms of message passing
algorithm um relying upon
different approximations to to posterior
probabilities those include um sort
of um trying to remember what the very
early ones I think the bound well Shard
algorithm and things like that were sort
of early versions of what then ended up
becoming fully basian type approaches
and the more General forms would be
things like variational message passing
which relies upon being filled
approximation so the idea that I can
factorize all my variables or the the
posterior probability over all the
different variables I'm dealing with and
by not having to deal with all the the
posterior covariances and conditional
dependences I can come up with a much
more efficient but still relatively good
and useful uh set beliefs about about
the causes of my
data um then there are more um more
accurate algorithms that were then uh
developed as well so things like belief
propagation some uh some product type
algorithms um which implicitly do take
account of pairwise dependences uh
between different variables but still
allow you to come up with good marginal
inferences uh often these rely upon
subtly different free energy
functionals so for instance belief
propagation implicitly comes from
something known as the BET free
energy which is
B um and that that effectively assumes
the posterior factorizes in such a way
that that I can take account of all the
pairwise uh dependencies and then
renormalize by all the Singleton so the
distributions of each single marginal in
my system and that allows you to to
achieve exact inference from the
perspective of the marginal
distributions you get out of the
end the point of doing all of these
sorts of things and you know there are
many others you expectation propagation
and various other based upon other free
energy approximations
and one more General is is kuchi free
energy that can be factorized again
different ways but the the purpose and
the advantage of doing most of these
things is that it allows us to
um to make use of the conditional
dependency structures the spacity
structures um and implicitly the markof
blankets in a um in a network and um ask
questions about specific variables solve
that in quite an efficient way to be
able to say what are the beliefs we have
about the idea behind the way this
equation is phrased is that you can
actually use those same messages and the
same cursive structures where um beliefs
depend upon the other beliefs in the
network and the message passing the
results of that to work out the
information gain about specific
variables so you can you can make use of
exactly the same um technology that was
used in things like belief propagation
schemes and which underwrite a lot of
neurobiological message passing
schemes so this message sorry this uh
equation um uses the notation CH to mean
children so that things upon which um
the things that depend upon the variable
we're interested in uh the parents um
which are the things that it depends
upon um
and those things and the parents of the
children she'll see so in a in a couple
of locations here which um together so
the children the parents and the the
parent the co-parents of of the same
children together make up the markof
blanket which is all the things that um
that if I knew about would give me all
the information I needed about the thing
I'm trying to infer so I only need to
know about the local blanket surrounding
a particular node and not the rest of
the network because if I know about
those things that tells me everything I
need to
know and so this is just a simple way
then of of um taking advantage of again
that sparcity to be able to come up with
efficient way estimating not just the
posteriors but the Information Gain I
could
potentially achieve about those
posterior given particular
policy or the information I could gain
about those variables Rel with posterior
relative to
Prior so the in the textbook there's an
example where the generative process and
the generative model have the same form
like if they're both generating from a
gaan then those distributions can truly
lock but also it's possible to have the
form of the generative process and the
generative model diff so like the
generative model is doing some
categorical two cold just right too hot
and then actually temperatures a
continuous variable and so on
so how how does the selection of family
of distribution that's even used relate
to the um in Information Gain like in
table one
uh okay I I think um I I'll just try and
unpick what I think possibly two
different things there so what one was
this notion of whether the generative
model that we might use are are prior
and likehood actually match the way in
which the the world rers generates those
data and I think that's a really
important thing to
consider and exactly as you say there
are often situations where um the best
model is in a sort of lay sense the
wrong model um in that it doesn't match
how data are actually generated um but
is a simpler explanation that it
complies with o razor and the reason for
that is you can always generate the same
data in a more complex way so if you can
get down to the simplest way of
generating it that's often the best way
one one of my favorite examples of this
was some um something I found out a
while back when when we were doing some
work on modeling of ir
movements and one of the things I found
is that it's much simpler to model your
eyes moving together as if you just had
one eye and then make predictions from
the perspective of both eyes because
both eyes move together you know
excluding sort of subtle things like
convergence um most of the time when you
want to decide upon a gaze Direction you
don't need to decide on separate gaze
directions for each eye you might have
you a chameleon or another sort of
creature that can move their eyes
independently but from our perspective
you can make do with a generative model
that is much simpler um than than the
physics of your eyes uh where actually
there's nothing to say that you couldn't
rotate two different spheres in
completely different
directions so by by doing that you
actually end up with a model that is
wrong but is also a much better model
than one that includes lots of
additional parameterization and degrees
of freedom that are just never used in
reality um so I think that that sort of
um is is quite a a nice intuitive
example of where your model might differ
from that in the world um and then
perhaps related to that is the other
point you were making about whether the
particular distributions in your model
are consistent with the distributions in
the
world um or even how do particular kinds
of
distribution um forgetting whether or
not they're they're accurate models of
the world how do they affect how you
then see seek
information um
and it it of course varies so um so one
of the reasons for including the table
that you showed is that the form for the
information gain will be different
depending upon which kind of you
have and that's just useful to know in
sensitive your writing down want to know
an efficient way of sampling from it
it's going to depend upon what format
model has yeah so one of the big
distinctions that we often see and often
make use of is this distinction between
categorical models and continuous
models um so the the um two middle rows
here are dealing with categorical or dis
lay uh
priors and they have a particular form
in terms of the information gain and the
way in which you do that
updating pull out that the ambiguity
bits and the predicted entropy bits um
the lowest Row third row shows the form
of a gy model and one of the key things
you can see in the gy model here is that
the um the covariance predicted so this
Sigma subscript y um is the prediction
of the predicted variance for the data
and so that is going to scale with the
ambiguity so you can immediately pull
out from that how much ambiguity there's
going to be just by looking at um at
this term here exactly one you high
highlighting um now if that depends upon
Pi then the ambiguity really matters if
that's constant as we saw in some of the
earlier ones and it doesn't depend upon
P then the only thing you need to take
account of is actually the first bit
which is the the um the maximum entropy
bit of of these
equations um so the form that you choose
for your model is absolutely key in
terms of how you then go about sampling
the world uh and how you optimize your
model is then absolutely dependent upon
how you've subel the world so you get
this sort of nice circularity that then
determines how you build your model
based upon what you see but based upon
how your model currently is and what's
uncertain about and what there is to
resolve you're going to considerably
change how you go about samping
it that's a really fascinating point and
it makes me think about
learning like in a given situation one
could over or under learn or however
comes to be that their policies do
matter for resolving
uncertainty and then that could set up
the balance
between continuing to sample from
distributions and or stopping
them yes that's an interesting draw
because you could start with a model in
which um don't know about how your
policy affects for example this Co
variance but it may be that over time
you realize that when I do this and end
up in this sort of State actually it
does affect
it or when when I take a particular
action and so if you then optimizing
your model and then then you go one step
further and you say well how do I how do
I learn which um or how do I infer which
parts my model will be affected by the
actions I take uh and how do I choose
the right action so that I can best
learn about which bits of my model will
be affected um and I think that's a a
really interesting question as to how
you might approach that so we could have
parameterized here or we could have
included additional parameters that are
how it does the covariance depend upon
policy and it might be that if those
parameters will Zero there's no
dependence all but as you learn more
about it might then learn actually there
is a a function that affects the
ambiguity uh and if that's the case then
I will change my behavior quite
considerably once I've learned where the
least ambiguous places
to connect this to language interfaces
and and chat and just different kinds of
of language models that people can
interact with so in human interacting
with with other and with how we design
these generative models to be this kind
of awareness of of
what parts could be influenced if I were
to prompt
this looking into the how much learning
would be expected from a distribution of
what responses are being generated from
the chatbot so like the distribution
that the chatbot
actually fleshes out is its irresolvable
uncertainty and then the question of
which prompt to enter next or which
prompt to
provide could be guided by wanting to
select the single best or from among the
best
next policy
selections to reduce some
uncertainty and so understand if it were
a
deterministic API on the other side like
a chess game then there would be only
the it would be a simplified decision of
what to prompt like a
calculator whereas with a probabilistic
model there's sometimes small sometimes
very
large uncertainties on what it actually
is out there so sometimes it it dwarfs
what can
be
resolved but we don't necessarily have
an awareness or ability to estimate in
these different situations what that
balance might
be however these these methods whether
the models
generating process is like an active
inference model or whatever happens to
be a sensor this can help interoperate
the different information resources and
patterns by putting them in a common
epistemic plus pragmatic Plus cost
setting yes I think that's right and if
you if You' got if you got a
sufficiently expressive
model that and a reasonable degree of
uncertainty about that model space you
can actually start to exactly learn how
you even go about doing these things
that as your model becomes more
sophisticated of the
world learn how to interact with it
better in in all three of those
domains
epistemic sorry two domains you you
mentioned three what's the third one
epistemic pragmatic and
cost ah okay so I normally think of the
pragmatic as as effectively yeah
compassing the cost but yes yeah
absolutely but the cost playing a
special clear role in this paper with a
finite stopping threshold for
sampling yeah
but but in a sense it it the it's not a
a sort so the cost is affecting the
samping but it's not sort of just
putting a clear time threshold on I'm
going to stop at this stage it's
something that sort of automatically
reweights itself relative to the amount
of information that might be left to
resolve I think that'll be something
very relevant that will be explored for
example if there is a value that can be
placed on a given piece of information
and that could be how much it influences
some trade or it could take into account
like the cost of paying the employee for
that much time or using the
computational resources then it's
possible to
allocate fixed or variable costs and
stopping
times with completely separated from the
epistemic and pragmatic generative model
itself
but with a cost as purely an exit
boundary and not be not directly
consuming the output of the free energy
calculations yes and that that made me
think of a couple of things so what what
one is that um that one of the
advantages of that sort of cost is that
in a dynamic environment it may be
appropriate at some points to rest and
then as uncertainty accumulates Beyond a
certain point you might want to go back
to sampling so you have a sort of time
or cut off after which you just
stop uh then then it's no good for
anything that might have
changed but if you if you've stopped for
a little while uh and decided not to put
in those costs you can then decide
when's the appropriate place to start S
not just a stop the other thing I
thought was interesting about about what
you said is is um again this notion that
that
to some extent although from an active
in perspective and certainly From
perspective of this paper information in
itself is
valuable uh and so the the value of
information is in terms of how
informative it is regardless of how it
affects what what um might gain in the
future however the how much you might
gain in the future may also be relevant
in terms of that pragmatic Mar um and
this brings in some of the ideas that
have come through St at inference like
schemes um where where you start to
evaluate these things recursively so in
in in a lot of reinforcement learning um
in probably most of it where there is
Information Gain it's
often um seen as the information that
will lead me to the uh the result I want
it will lead me to more reward uh and so
creatures May learn a path through their
environment that um that is the one that
more reliably leads them to reward
because it tells them where to go
earlier on something those lines um
however that one could say that that and
that is important but one one could also
say that it's important to learn about
your environment for its own sake as
well and one of the things active
inference does is it doesn't put any
special
um focus on either the Fulfillment of
your preferences or the seeking of
information but the interesting
connection between the two is that often
seeking out information will help you
fulfill your preferences in the future
and so if you're able to recursively
evaluate if I knew this what would I do
uh and if I did that what would I learn
and if I knew that and keep going into
the future you can also select uh things
that will give you information that will
help you satisfy your your pragmatic
value as well so information ends up
having a dual purpose first of all in
being valuable in its own sake but also
being Val in terms of what else you can
can gain from it in the future both in
terms of information but also in terms
of in terms of the um pragmatic value to
be able to
achieve I think we'll we'll come to that
with the um pragmatics of epistemic
value but just one note on the message
passing
uh you mentioned how with the stop in
Criterion it's possible to think about
the information foraging setting not
just as like where to look every time a
metronome clicks but bout scheduling
bouts like batching emails or something
like that and that reminded me of our
recent discussion with some of the RX
and fur team about the RX environment
package which uses the reactive message
passing to uncouple the time in of for
example the nestmate and the niche in a
generative model so that they can be on
different timings and the computations
occur on demand like in a node local way
and can have uncoupled timings so it's
just very interesting how this pathway
that is laid out in the paper about how
on one hand we have the
graphical semantic layout of what these
variables are and then how many
preparation
stages before it all gets played out as
the relationship of the equations that
we get from the
entropies so in a sense this is sort of
setting out the process that that um
someone might go through if they were
trying to unpack this this sort of
modeling in practice you might asse that
actually a lot of it just starts from
this message passing stage as it's the
interaction directly with message
passing and what you
sample and a lot of the graphics along
top really to set out the equivalence
between different sorts of
formalism which some people are very
familiar with using one sort in
principle you could tell this story
without referring to a Bas of network
without referring to a fact graph um
and one of the big focuses really here
was just trying to point out the way in
which they they're inter
related Carl or Christopher we can go
any
[Music]
direction you I go in two directions
because there two really interesting
issues there just you I can't resist um
perhaps in reverse order that you the
notion of reactive message passing I
think um is not only crucial and again
very biometic uh but also um very
relevant in terms of computer science
and efficiency in you know in terms of
implementing um any kind of active
inference or learning scheme um it
actually inherits from something called
the actor model in computer science
which is a big thing which led to the
development of a whole Suite of
different programming langu which is you
know um one of the most popular nowadays
is rust um that is predicated very much
on this notion of um responding to to
queries and um requests for computation
and the products of that computation
which it's very very comfortably with um
the you know the maths of message
passing on Factor graphs so I think the
RX infer reactive message passing is
exactly the right way to go not only in
terms of understanding biometic Dy DCS
and belief updating but also in
engineering the next generation of um
deep learning or artificial intelligence
of a more generalized sort um but the
other direction I wanted to come back to
this I think really important discussion
about is information is the value of
information intrinsic to the information
gain or is it always conditioned upon
your ultimate goal um I think that's a
really quite a profound uh point um and
I have a very specific take on that that
inherits from the physics you get from
the free energy principle so if you just
write down what is the probability
distribution over paths into the
future and then you take the logarithm
um of that probability to create a
potential that is the expected free
energy so the expected free energy that
can become carved into the expected
Information Gain and the expected log
PRI preference or expected value falls
out of the physics of
self-organization and that decomposition
tells you that these things are linearly
separable it means that there is no
value of information about the reward
that does not exist because about the
reward suggests you can't linearly
separate the expected information game
from the expected value so this
notion I think that you um only have to
learn about that which you need to know
in order to get your reward I think it's
fundamentally wrong and one has to ask
where did it come from and I think it's
by putting a certain kind of teeology
and semantics on the physics of
sentience and you know senent behavior
that leads you to that false conclusion
because now what does value mean well
everything has to be in relation to the
reward or the
goal but of course the value of
information is
not another another way of looking or if
you like um dissolving that that sort of
um disconnect between the intrinsic
value of resolving your uncertainty
about the world as opposed to the
extrinsic value of avoiding expected
surprise um where surprise is read as a
sort of negative log of your prior
preferences
is just to think about uh to acknowledge
that we're talking about um effectively
lran or potential functions because
they're log probabilities so when I say
you can linearly separate them what we
are separating in a linear
non-interacting way are the log
probabilities when you actually combine
the two probabilities what that actually
means is that I will only go for
Information Gain if it satisfies my um
my goals or equivalently and
symmetrically um I am only going to
satisfy my goals if I get a sufficiently
high Information Gain so they both
contextualize each other in probability
space even though uh they are L they
don't interact in terms of information
or um in terms of potentials or log
probabilities the final point is that
you
know this non theological compilation of
the value of information and the value
of conforming to the constraints
supplied by the prior
preferences is
that that is exactly what you get when
acknowledging that the free energy
principle is dual to James's principle
of constrainted Maximum
entropy so in this instance you can just
rewrite or re your
reinterpret um the free energy Principle
as an instance of constraint maximum
entropy principle and you were talking
before about you know the benefits of
Maximum entropy and this is one very
simple instantiation of it where the
entropy in question is the entropy of
your posterior or your measurement but
it's
constrained so now
rewards are just ways of writing down
constraints on an information maximizing
system or a maximum entropy um uh system
and where do those constraints come from
they come from the generative model
where does the Gen model what
constitutes generative model it's just
the prior preferences in your generative
model from the point of view of the free
energy principle so by if you like
appealing not just to the free energy
principle but James's constraint Maxim
entry principle mathematically that
speaks to a very very clear picture that
the intrinsic value of information has
got nothing to do with Rewards or goals
or constraints it's just a way of
writing down a constraint and you can
actually articulate this in terms of The
Grange multipliers um where you can
either look at the information seeking
as constraint by reward or you can look
at reward seeking as constrained by uh
information but in log space they're
completely
independent that's that's what came to
mind I think it's a really interesting
point which is you know confused me for
years and and you know also is a
recurrent question when you talk to
people in reinforcement learning who
have this if like gamblers fallacy about
you the relationship between the two
kinds of uh two kinds of
value thank you Carl that was amazing a
few
notes the additivity of the log
probabilities is
the in the is the um multiplication of
the
probabilities non log so just properties
of logs so it's fascinating how they are
both cross calibrated and
referenced and decomposed from
generalized free energy or expected free
energy
considerations and in practice there's
the parameterization of uh what the
actual values are however you have given
a very full-throated defense of the pure
value of of Information
Gain and that was something in the in
the approach of this paper that
Christopher and I had explored a little
bit how it starts with the information
gain and
then the end of the paper brings
in the pragmatic
value as opposed to looking to expand
the epistemic scope of reward and
reinforcement and introduce some kind of
variability or learning or or
intelligence layer other than that
starting with the information gain and
then tuning the regimes of attention and
action from there so that's very um
interesting Chris what do you have any
other thoughts or directions
no I think that uh that really
everything's kind of been captured here
um very nicely and I'm still trying to
process through some of the things that
we've discussed now um I just really
appreciate how the paper's written how
well it has it you know mentioning what
Daniel said how it builds from a single
kernel of information uh Mutual
Information Gain uh and then it just
builds out the model from there into
something that is more and more
applicable to different regimes so you
can kind of stop at each point that you
any point at any point that you want um
and then it just kind of grows into
something that is you know immediately
applicable to clinical trials which is
quite wonderful and I really did
appreciate that um I'm just going to
have to sit through and probably process
some of the things that uh we've
discussed here
today yeah I think that uh let's just in
the last minutes think about what we
might want to process over the next week
and prepare some questions it might be
cool to see the code so Thomas if you
want to have it loaded up or we can uh
try to prepare it on one of our machines
Christopher um we uh yeah or Thomas what
what would you look forward to
discussing or
doing if if if you'd like to it's it's
it's all available on um on uh GitHub
repository um and I think it's set up so
that if it's run it will generate a
series of animations showing process of
sampling as
well so I if if you could if you could
yeah that would be awesome
yeah let's um return on that and look at
the code what's the easiest thing would
you like me to send you something there
oh if you could just prepare to share
your screen with the code running and
then we can start with the the just a
little bit of looking at it just seeing
what the code does and then in the in
the second part talk more about the
clinical trial setting and how it it um
is all brought together in the section
six
sounds good
cool any last thoughts from any of
you I'm
here thank you Thomas and Carl this is
awesome
to have you join thank you Chris for
helping prepare this too so all right
see you next time thank you guys have a
good one bye for